<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<taxonomy>
	<title>E-mail based phishing attack taxonomy</title>
	<description>E-mail based phishing attack taxonomy, which includes six phases of the attack. Each phase has at least one criterion for the attack categorization. Each category is described and in some cases have sub-classes to present the full variety of phishing attacks.</description>
	<authors>
		<person>Justinas Rastenis</person>
		<person>Simona Ramanauskaitė</person>
		<person>Justinas Janulevičius</person>
		<person>Antanas Čenys</person>
		<person>Asta Slotkienė</person>
	</authors>
	<contributors>
		<person>Unknown reviewer of journal "Applied Sciences"</person>
	</contributors>
	<structure>
		<phase>
			<title>E-mail address selection</title>
			<description>In order to execute an e-mail-based phishing attack an e-mail address or addresses of the potential victim have to be obtained. In this phase different strategies for e-mail address selection are used, therefore we divide the address selection phase into strategy types for e-mail address selection.</description>
			<classifier>
				<title>E-mail address selection strategy</title>
				<description>Strategy how the attacker select an e-mail addresses as possible victims</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Usage of existing e-mail address</title>
						<description>E-mail addresses are obtained from different sources to make sure its existing, real address</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>Web crawled e-mail</title>
								<description>E-mail address crawled, obtained from web pages, where e-mail addresses are presented as contacts or for other purposes.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>E-mail from previous phishing attack</title>
								<description>Some phishing attacks seek to get e-mail address as the next victims address, therefore phishing attack can be a source for e-mail address gaining too.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>E-mail from other systems</title>
								<description>Attacker can get access to different systems, where e-mail addresses might be stored. The variety of possible systems is very big, therefore we do not divide it into smaller ones.</description>
							</value>						
						</values>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Generation of e-mail addresses</title>
						<description>E-mail addresses are generated, not obtained from some source</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>Domain based generation</title>
								<description>E-mail address is generated by using typical (admin, sales, etc) or specific (name.surname, department, etc) local part plus the known domain</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Other techniques</title>
								<description>Different techniques can be used for e-mail address generation (local part is selested and domain name is brute forces, etc). The number of possible solutions is not limited and listed.</description>
							</value>						
						</values>					
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
		</phase>
		<phase>
			<title>E-mail content creation</title>
			<description>The content, text of the e-mail for phishing attack has to be prepared to involve the victim into the phishing attack. This phase is very important and can be classified based on multiple criteria. We define four criteria for e-mail content creation for phishing attack: idea for victim involvement in the phishing attack; e-mail text generation strategy; e mail text creator type; e-mail text personalization level. </description>
			<classifier>
				<title>Ideas for the victim involvement in the phishing attack</title>
				<description>Phichological environment influences user actions, therefore the e-mail content is generated to create desired effect</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Benefit</title>
						<description>Benefit proposal motivates the victim to provide requested data in order to get some financial or other benefit from it. However, in most cases the promised benefit is not provided, while the gathered data is used for different purposes.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>"Legitimate" request</title>
						<description>Impression of legitimate request does not involve additional questions on request legitimacy and victim automatically sends the requested data. However, it is very difficult to generate such an e-mail text, providing sufficient amount of details about request management processes and internal data.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Important information</title>
						<description>Impression of an important event. Information request leads to stress for the victim, therefore some victims do not analyze the e-mail with sufficient attention and proceed with a hurry to execute the requested actions, providing the requested data.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Possible failure</title>
						<description>Impression of a possible failure in case data the data is not provided. It is a very similar strategy to the previous one as it activates the same emotions for the victim. At the same time, it is more focused on understanding the internal processes, as the attacker must know or imagine what kind of processes might be associated to failure if data is not provided by the victim.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Other</title>
						<description>Other strategies are possible too. The phishing attack is much harder to identify if it is using some very specific weaknesses of the victim, as the traditional phishing attack e-mail texts are well known and are easy to recognize as a phishing attack.</description>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
			<classifier>
				<title>E-mail text generation strategy</title>
				<description>The attacker defines how the e-mail text will be generated.</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Generated</title>
						<description>A new, case-specific phishing attack text. It might be time consuming, however, is harder to identify it as a phishing attack by signature based e-mail filtering systems.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Edited</title>
						<description>The e-mail text is copied from another e-mail (legitimate or phishing attack e-mail) and some parts of the e-mail are changed (replacing the name of the receiver etc.).</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Duplicated</title>
						<description>The e-mail text is copied from other sources and is not changed at all.</description>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
			<classifier>
				<title>E-mail text creator</title>
				<description>E-mail text can be created manually or by using a automated solutions</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Human</title>
						<description>E-mail text is written or changed by person</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Robot, computer</title>
						<description>R-mail text is generated or modified by computer program, robot.</description>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
			<classifier>
				<title>E-mail text personalization level</title>
				<description>E-mail text personalization level is closely related to the e-mail text generation strategy and defines the ammount of personal victims information ammount in the e-mail.</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>not personalized</title>
						<description>the e-mail text is very abstract and no personal information is added in the e-mail.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>personalized</title>
						<description>the e-mail text includes some personalized information about the receiver or the e-mail.</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>publicly available data</title>
								<description>Publicly available data about the victim or its organziation (such as name, surname, title of the organization etc.) is included in the e-mail. Personalized phishing attacks with publicly available victim data is called spear phishing.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>specific knowledge</title>
								<description>More specific knowledge about the victim or its organization (such as recent user’s visits, financial operations, etc.) can be added to the e-mail. personalized phishing attacks where using some specific knowledge and usually directed to some higher position persons are classed whaling attacks.</description>
							</value>
						</values>
					</value>
				</values>					
			</classifier>
		</phase>
		<phase>
			<title>Sending the e-mail to recipients</title>
			<description>The method, how the attacker sends the e-mail to possible phishing victim is an important factor. The selected phishing attack strategy is implemented by sending the phishing e-mails, therefore we detail the e-mail sending phase based on three criteria: senders e-mail address usage; number of receivers in the phishing attack; usage of systemic phishing attack strategy. </description>
			<classifier>
				<title>Senders e-mail address</title>
				<description>Senders e-mail address is one of the main factors to identify phishing attack. The attacker can use his real or spoofed e-mail address</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Real e-mail address</title>
						<description>Real e-mail address uses no specific techniques to change it. The attacker might use hacked e-mail account or registers, creates untraceable e-mail account for phishing e-mail distribution.</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>Hacked</title>
								<description>The hacker do not own the e-mail account but uses someones account. In most cases it is e-mail accounts with gained access, but different techniqes can be used to use someones e-mail account.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Owned</title>
								<description>The hacker creates or registers its own e-mail account and uses it for phishing accunt. In most cases the domain is very similar to some specific domain, but has some minor changes.</description>
							</value>
						</values>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Spoofed e-mail address</title>
						<description>spoofed e-mail addresses are changed to trick the victim by showing some specific e-mail address, which is not possible to obtain legitimately.</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>Targeted</title>
								<description>The e-mail address spoofed to mimic some specific, targeted e-mail address. It matches exactly to a selected e-mail address.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Camouflage</title>
								<description>The aim is to generate very similar e-mail address to a legitimate one, but no identical match needed.</description>
							</value>
						</values>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>	
			<classifier>
				<title>Number of receivers</title>
				<description>Number of receivers in the phishing attack can be used for phishing attack identification and should be associated to the number of receivers only (not based on the text of the e-mail)</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Individual</title>
						<description>e-mail receiver is one address. Multiple e-mails are sent at the same time, but it is individual, if the victim is able to see his or her own e-mail address as the receiver.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Group</title>
						<description>e-mail receivers are multiple e-mail addresses. The usage of multiple addresses might be used as an additional method to illustrate the sender knows multiple, related e¬¬-mails in the organization, multiple e-mails of the same person, or stimulate concurrency between several victims to get the benefit before somebody else did.</description>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
			<classifier>
				<title>Systematic strategy</title>
				<description>Usage of systematic phishing attack strategy allows higher phishing attack success possibility, however requires additional actions and knowledge about the victim</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Non-systematic</title>
						<description>Non-systematic strategy requires no additional actions, usually sends one phishing attack e-mail and then waits for the results.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>systematic</title>
						<description>systematic phishing attacks require additional actions and knowledge. The simplest case is sending of multiple e-mails to the same victim by remembering or adding some additional information in the later e-mails. Another solution is to contact the victim within other channels (phone call, social networks, etc.). The usage of another communication channels is used to remember about the e-mail or to motivate to act, convince in legitimacy of the request. The motivation and convincing can be achieved by involving other persons too (contacting different persons individually and motivating to collaborate or change information between them). There may be other specific cases (related information publishing in the media, etc.) when some additional attacker actions are executed to implement attack strategy.</description>
						<values id="systematicActions">
							<value>
								<title>Send multiple e-mails</title>
								<description>The attacker composes the phishing attack of multiple e-mails. Some e-mails require the information or victim actions, later e-mail remind of it etc.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Contack within other channels</title>
								<description>The attacker additionally uses different communication channels to motivate victim to act. In some cases it is a phone call, instance messaging connection etc.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Involve other persons</title>
								<description>The attacker creates a network of victims and multiple persons are involved in the same attack. For example one person can receive an e-mail message by presenting some fake information, while another receives an e-mail with additional reference the firt person can provide additional information etc.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Other methods</title>
								<description>Different methods can be used to compose a solid phishing attack strategy, therefore some very specific, can be covered by this category.</description>
							</value>
						</values>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>			
		</phase>	
		<phase>
			<title>Waiting for the response from the email receivers</title>
			<description>In most cases the attacker just waits for the victim to respond to the phishing e-mail. However, in the case of systematic strategy of phishing attack, some additional actions can be executed while waiting for the victim’s response. </description>
			<classifier>
				<title>Actions</title>
				<description>While hacker is waiting the victim to response he or she can do some additional actions. Those actions are associated to systematic phishing attack only, as with non-systematic the hacker simply waits.</description>
				<values idref="systematicActions"/>
			</classifier>
		</phase>
		<phase>
			<title>Phishing attack results, data gathering</title>
			<description>The main purpose of phishing attack is to get some specific data from the victim. We recommend defining the phase of gathered data based on data gathering environment as well as types of gathered data. </description>
			<classifier>
				<title>Data gathering environment</title>
				<description>Data gathering environment defines how the attacker gets the information and what kind of environment is used for it</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>E-mail</title>
						<description>Reply is one of the main victim actions, as it requires no additional investment for data gathering tools – the user replies to the received e-mail by providing requested data.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Web page</title>
						<description>Web page is very popular data gathering environment. The attacker creates a web page with data input functionality. Some web sites are unique, while others mimic, spoof other systems and trick the user to think they use some legitimate web site, while submitting the data to the attacker.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Other</title>
						<description>Other types of data gathering during phishing attack are used too. Attackers can attach malicious code, use social networks, phones etc.</description>
					</value>
				</values>	
			</classifier>
			<classifier>
				<title>Types of gathered data</title>
				<description>Types of gathered data varies in different phishing attacks and is the main puspose of the phishing attack.</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Association</title>
						<description>Association desines the data, needed to generate the victim’s profile from publicly available data, however because of the big amount of related data the data has to be associated, to assure integrity of the user profile. In some cases, the existence of such an e-mail is enough from the victim, in other cases some publicly available personal data is gathered from the victims response.</description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>E-mail address confirmation</title>
								<description>Sometimes the victims e-mail is not clear and the ohishing attach can be aimed to find out is the used e-mail is real and belongs to the victim.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>User profile public data</title>
								<description>Not private, publicly available users data can be faund in the internet, however sometimes the hacker needs a confirmations its a correct data, belongs to this, not similar person etc.</description>
							</value>
						</values>						
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Secret data</title>
						<description>Secret data is more valuable in phishing attack but at the same time it is harder to get from the victim. </description>
						<values>
							<value>
								<title>Logins</title>
								<description>User credentials, logins to a specific systems.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Financial data</title>
								<description>Financial data is very sensitive as can be used for financial frauds, therefore credit card numbers, security codes are very desired for financial frauds.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Company data</title>
								<description>Company data can contain some sensitive information, related to bussiness secrets, systems its using etc.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Personally identifiable information</title>
								<description>Personal victims data (date of birth, social security number, etc.) can be used as basis for identity chief or more sophisticated phishing attacks.</description>
							</value>
							<value>
								<title>Other</title>
								<description>Phishing attacks might be targeted on very specific data, therefore any other information from the victim can be requested by the hacker.</description>
							</value>
						</values>												
					</value>
				</values>				
			</classifier>			
		</phase>
		<phase>
			<title>Usage of gathered results, data</title>
			<description>While the usage of gathered data is a little bit out of scope, it is very closely related to gathered data, therefore we highlight the phase of gathered data usage and list possible purposes the attacker might have by using the phishing attack gathered data.</description>
			<classifier>
				<title>Data usage purpose</title>
				<description>Purpose of phishing attack data usage is closely related to the type of gathered data during the phishing attack</description>
				<values>
					<value>
						<title>Access gaining</title>
						<description>Access gaining to some specific system. If login data is gathered during phishing attack, the same logins might apply to get access to this or even other systems of the same victim.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Financial frauds</title>
						<description>Financial frauds are related to financial and personal victim’s data. In some cases the phishing attack leads to victim actions, where the victim transfers their money to the attacker by believing they are executing some legitimate money transfer to a different source.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>User/company system hacking</title>
						<description>User/company system hacking is related to access gaining, but sometimes the phishing attack is oriented to collect some specific data on enterprise management structure, used technologies etc.</description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Identity theft/fraud</title>
						<description>Identity theft occurs when someone uses another's personally identifying information, like their name, identifying number, or credit card number, without their permission, to commit fraud or other crimes. </description>
					</value>
					<value>
						<title>Other</title>
						<description>Other types of purposes of the phishing attack exist, however it is not as often and it varies a lot, therefore the other class added to fit all of them.</description>
					</value>
				</values>
			</classifier>
		</phase>	
	</structure>
</taxonomy>